Guide to the Patriotic Envelope Collection [1861-1865], 1898 PR 117
New-York Historical Society
- Series I: Civil War Envelopes, 1
  - Satan: Secession is nearly played out. (Offsite-box 4, Item 11)
    The devil running, holding a pitchfork that flies the Confederate flag. Beige envelope with black ink. Image on left.
  - Satan: The Root of Treason (Offsite-box 4, Item 7)
    The devil depicted as a gnarled tree root. White envelope with blue ink. Image on left side.
    Creator: New-York Union Envelope Depot
  - Satan: The traitor Arnold (Offsite-box 4, Item 15)
  - Satan: The innocent cause of all the trouble. (Offsite-box 4, Item 14)
    Devil sitting on a bail of cotton. Cream envelope with black ink. Image on left.
  - Satan: [Devil and whiskey] (Offsite-box 4, Item 3)
    Devil sitting hunched over a whiskey barrel holding a flag. White envelope with red and blue ink. Image on left side.
    Creator: Simson & Co., designer and publisher
  - Satan: An eminent southern clergyman. (Offsite-box 4, Item 13)
    Clergyman at the pulpit with bible on it with the devil standing beside him. Each has one hand on the open bible. Beige envelope with black ink. Image on left.
  - Satan: Uncle Sam cutting down the "secession tree." (Offsite-box 4, Item 16)
    Uncle Sam swinging an axe to cut down a palm tree flying the Confederate flag. The devil looks on saying "woodman, spare that tree." White envelope with blue ink. Image on left. "Phil" inscribed in pencil on seal.
  - Satan: The First Secessionist (Offsite-box 4, Item 5)
    The Devil holding a pitchfork. Beige envelope with black ink. Image on left side.
  - Ships: The (bark) Great West. (Offsite-box 4, Item 28)
    Three-masted ship above "Great West." A boat rowed by slaves barely able to hold its sacks of grain, above "Great South.". Cream envelope with blue ink. Images side by side.
    Creator: Mumford & Co.
  - Ships: Capt. Baker, of the pirate "Savannah." (Offsite-box 4, Item 15)
    Captain Baker wearing large hat looking shocked. Yellow envelope with black ink. Image on top-left.
  - Ships: A flying rumour for Jeff. Davis' "private-ear." (Offsite-box 4, Item 25)
    Ship flying the American flag at sea. White envelope with blue ink. Image on left side.
  - Ships: Privateering under difficulties. (Offsite-box 4, Item 4)
    Large ship with full sails labeled "United States" and flying the American flag chases a small ship with empty sails labeled "Jefferson Davis" and flying the Confederate flag. Yellow envelope with red and blue ink. Image on left.
  - Ships: Jeff's navy (Offsite-box 4, Item 21)
    Jefferson Davis and Confederate sailors floating in a teacup that flies a flag bearing a skull and crossbones. White envelope with blue ink. Image on left.
  - Ships: The impending crisis (Offsite-box 4, Item 29)
    Three sailors at sea in a teacup flying the Confederate flag spy a large sailing ship flying the American flag on the horizon. White envelope with black ink. Image on left.
  - Ships: Our country before the war. (Offsite-box 4, Item 26)
    Ship at dock with loads of provisions on pier and in foreground. Blue envelope with red ink. Image on left-top.
  - Ships: The C. S. A. man of war. (Offsite-box 4, Item 16)
    Jefferson Davis, dressed as a woman, floating in a washtub labeled "Lady Davis," which flies the Confederate flag. Beige envelope with black ink. Image on left. Embossed decoration on seal.
    Creator: Zahm, F. H. & Co.
  - Ships: Master Jeff - and his navy. (Offsite-box 4, Item 18)
    Jefferson Davis, standing next to a washtub, holding a toy boat that flies a Confederate flag and a skull and crossbones banner. Cream envelope with blue ink. Image on left.
  - Soldiers and Sailors: The soldier's dream (Offsite-box 4, Item 10)
    Union soldiers rest at camp. In cloud above is scene of a soldier being welcomed home by his family. Inset is seal with eagles and American shield. White envelope with blue ink. Image on left.
  - Soldiers and Sailors: The young volunteer. (Offsite-box 4, Item 68)
    Soldier holds American flag. White envelope with colored ink. Image on left.
    Creator: Cutter, Tower & Co., copyright holder
  - Soldiers and Sailors: The defenders of our union. (Offsite-box 4, Item 35)
    A soldier and a sailor, both waiving their hats in the air, stand in from on of a monument to the Union. White envelope with brown ink. Image on top-left.
  - Soldiers and Sailors: The way our Union boys are raised. (Offsite-box 4, Item 29)
    Boy seated outdoors on a basket of wheat holding a bow. White envelope with blue ink. Image on top-left.
  - Soldiers and Sailors: Our army and navy forever. (Offsite-box 4, Item 30)
    Sailor, seated with package, anchor, sextant, and spyglass, with ship in background. White envelope with blue ink. Image on left.
  - Soldiers and Sailors: Forward march to Richmond. (Offsite-box 4, Item 14)
    Five soldiers holding weapons and instruments. White envelope with blue ink. Image on top-left.
  - Soldiers and Sailors: [Battle between Union and Confederate soldiers.] (Offsite-box 4, Item 11)
    Battle between Union and Confederate soldiers. White envelope with colored ink. Image covers sheet.
  - Soldiers and Sailors: [African-American soldier.] (Offsite-box 4, Item 8)
    African-American soldier wearing a base-drum on his back. With lines and printed indications for address including: reg't., Co., Col., Com'g, and Camp. Cream envelope with blue ink. Image on left.
    Creator: Bond, J. W. & Co.
  - Soldiers and Sailors: [Union] (Offsite-box 4, Item 9)
    Union Soldier in uniform with overcoat and hat. With lines and printed indications for address including: reg't., Co., Col., Com'g, and Camp. Cream envelope with black ink. Image on left.
    Creator: King & Baird
  - Soldiers and Sailors: [Union soldier in battle.] (Offsite-box 4, Item 23)
    Revolutionary War soldier in battle with American flag and drum in background. White envelope with black ink and applied color. Image on left.
  - Soldiers and Sailors: Flag of the seas! (Offsite-box 4, Item 52)
    Sailor holds American flag with seated woman in foreground. White envelope with blue ink. Image on left.
  - Soldiers and Sailors: Union Jack sending one of Jeff Davis' pirates to "Davy Jones' locker." (Offsite-box 4, Item 39)
    Union sailor watching as a man wearing boats marked with the skull and crossbones falls through a hole in a ship's deck. White envelope with blue ink. Image on left.
  - Soldiers and Sailors: Bound to wave. (Offsite-box 4, Item 57)
    Sailor with sword drawn and foot on anchor holds American flag. White envelope with colored ink. Image on left. Addressed to Mr. Isaac P. Ball, esq., Fish Kill Landing, Duchess Co. NY. Return address: William R. Green. Postmarked Wash. D.C., Aug. 7.
  - Soldiers and Sailors: The captured battery. (Offsite-box 4, Item 93)
    Union soldier stands beside cannon waiving hat and shouting. Slain soldier lays at his feet. White envelope with red ink. Image at left.
  - Soldiers and Sailors: The first step in the art of war. (Offsite-box 4, Item 24)
    Line of six Confederate soldiers running (seen from behind.) White envelope with gray ink. Image on left.
  - Soldiers and Sailors: Hatteras. (Offsite-box 4, Item 46)
    Union sailor standing in front of flag, shield, and eagle. White envelope with gray ink. Image on left with "Hatteras" printed across top-right.
  - States--Border--Kentucky: Kentucky (Offsite-box 4, Item 1)
    Kentucky state seal. White envelope with blue ink. Image on left.
  - States--Border--Maryland: The great seal of Maryland (Offsite-box 4, Item 1)
    Maryland state seal. White envelope with blue ink. Image on left.
  - States--Border--Maryland: The long and short of it. (Offsite-box 4, Item 11)
    Small rooster looks up at a tall bird that eats the fruit from the top of a palm tree. White envelope with black ink. Image on top-left.
  - States--Border--Missouri: State of Missouri (Offsite-box 4, Item 3)
    Liberty in clouds, holding American flag and Missouri state seal. White envelope with brown ink. Image on left with "union" on top-right in stars and stripes.
  - States--Border--Missouri: Poor deluded Miss-Souri (Offsite-box 4, Item 1)
    Woman stepping into a tub, labeled "secession," that is full of very hot water. White envelope with black ink. Image on left.
  - States--Confederate--Alabama: Alabama (Offsite-box 4, Item 1)
    The devil holds the Alabama state seal and a Confederate flag. White envelope with red ink. Image on left with text on top-right.
  - States--Confederate--Arkansas: Arkansas (Offsite-box 4, Item 1)
    Arkansas state seal. White envelope with blue ink. Image on left.
    Creator: Reagles & Co., copyright holder
  - States--Confederate--Florida: Florida (Offsite-box 4, Item 1)
    The devil holds the Florida state seal and a Confederate flag. White envelope with green ink. Image on left with text on top-right.
  - States--Confederate--Georgia: Where did the money go? (Offsite-box 4, Item 8)
    A corn cob. Blue envelope with red and yellow ink. Image on top-left.
  - States--Confederate--Louisiana: Running the blockade. (Offsite-box 4, Item 2)
    Man riding on the tail of an alligator with a crate labeled "For New Orleans and a market." White envelope with blue ink. Image on top-left.
  - States--Confederate--Mississippi: Mississippi (Offsite-box 4, Item 1)
    The devil holds the Mississippi state seal and a Confederate flag. White envelope with blue ink. Image on left with text on top-right.
  - States--Confederate--North Carolina: North Carolina (Offsite-box 4, Item 2)
    The devil holds the North Carolina state seal and a Confederate flag. White envelope with orange ink. Image on left with text on top-right.
  - States--Confederate--South Carolina: Southern independence (Offsite-box 4, Item 14)
    Flag bearing a palm tree and the words "Southern independence." Cream envelope with blue ink. Image on top-left.
  - States--Confederate--South Carolina: Gen'l Sherman's Headquarters, Hilton Head, S.C. (Offsite-box 4, Item 1)
    Scene of a camp, with a sentry walking. Tents, wagons and ships are in the background. Cream envelope with gray ink. Image covers most of envelope.
  - States--Confederate--South Carolina: South Carolina (Offsite-box 4, Item 3)
    South Carolina state seal. White envelope with black ink. Image on left.
    Creator: Union Stationery Depot
  - States--Confederate--Tennessee: Tennessee (Offsite-box 4, Item 1)
    Tennessee state seal. White envelope with blue ink. Image on left.
  - States--Confederate--Texas: Texas (Offsite-box 4, Item 1)
    The devil holds the Texas state seal and a Confederate flag. White envelope with blue ink. Image on left with text on top-right.
  - States--Confederate--Virginia: Poor old simple Virginia (Offsite-box 4, Item 2)
    Woman, labeled "old dominion," stoops over as Union and Confederate soldiers climb onto her and do battle on her back. White envelope with red ink. Image on left.
  - States--Confederate--Virginia: Virginny (Offsite-box 4, Item 25)
    An old woman is surprised by a skull coming out of a teapot. Cream envelope with blue ink. Image on left.
  - States--Confederate--Virginia: How Virginia was voted out of the Union. (Offsite-box 4, Item 10)
    Voting booth with "yes" and "no" windows. A man trying to vote "no" on secession is met with a gun in his face. Yellow envelope with black ink. Image on top left.
  - States--Confederate--Virginia: West Virginia - East Virginia (Offsite-box 4, Item 7)
    A man, labeled "West Virginia," pulls a donkey, labeled "East Virginia," by the tail as it tries to jump off a cliff. White envelope with black ink. Image on left.
  - States--Confederate--Virginia: Virginia in 1776 / Virginia in 1861 (Offsite-box 4, Item 14)
    Top image: a dignified woman reading to a group of well-mannered young men. Bottom image: the same woman, drunk and unkempt, surrounded by gamblers, thieves, and a man waving the Confederate flag. White envelope with black ink. Images on left.
  - States--Connecticut: Qui. Trans. Sust. Post. Nub. Phoeb. (Offsite-box 4, Item 1)
    Seal with deer in center, flags and eagle. White envelope with blue ink. Image on left.
  - States--Connecticut: Connecticut (Offsite-box 4, Item 18)
    Liberty, holding banner bearing title and motto, sits with American shield, eagle, and Connecticut state seal. White envelope with orange ink. Image on left with banner across top and shield in top-right corner.
  - States--Connecticut: The charter oak (Offsite-box 4, Item 10)
    Oak tree. Beige envelope with black ink. Image on top-left. Embossed decoration on seal.
  - States--Delaware: State of Delaware (Offsite-box 4, Item 1)
    Liberty, wrapped in American flag, holds Delaware state seal. White envelope with red and blue ink. Image on left. Border and decorative pattern cover sheet.
  - States--Illinois: State of Illinois (Offsite-box 4, Item 1)
    Liberty in clouds, holding American flag and Illinois state seal. White envelope with colored ink. Image on left with "Union" on top-right in stars and stripes.
    Creator: Riderburgh, William, vendor
  - States--Indiana: Indiana (Offsite-box 4, Item 1)
    Indiana state seal. White envelope with blue ink. Image on left.
  - States--Iowa: Iowa (Offsite-box 4, Item 1)
    Liberty, holding American flag and leaning on Iowa state seal, with Confederate flag beneath her foot. White envelope with blue ink. Image on left with "Union" and " Iowa" on top-right.
  - States--Kansas: Kansas (Offsite-box 4, Item 1)
    Kansas state seal.
  - States--Maine: Maine (Offsite-box 4, Item 1)
    Maine state seal over American flag. White envelope with brown ink. Image on left.
  - States--Massachusetts: Honor to the glorious old bay state (Offsite-box 4, Item 2)
    Massachusetts state seal. White envelope with red ink. Image on left (vertical orientation.)
  - States--Massachusetts: Massachusetts (Offsite-box 4, Item 1)
    Massachusetts state seal between two American flags. White envelope with black ink. Image covers sheet.
  - States--Michigan: Michigan (Offsite-box 4, Item 1)
    Michigan state seal.
    Creator: Berlin & Jones, manufacturers
  - States--Minnesota: Minnesota (Offsite-box 4, Item 1)
    Liberty, holding American flag and leaning on Minnesota state seal, with Confederate flag beneath her foot. White envelope with blue ink. Image on left with "Union" and " Minnesota" on top-right.
  - States--Nebraska: State of Nebraska (Offsite-box 4, Item 1)
    Liberty, wrapped in American flag, holds Nebraska state seal. White envelope with red and blue ink. Image on left. Border and decorative pattern cover sheet.
    Creator: Reagles & Co., designer and manufacturer
  - States--New Hampshire: State of New Hampshire (Offsite-box 4, Item 3)
    Liberty, wrapped in American flag, holds New Hampshire state seal. White envelope with red and blue ink. Image on left. Border and decorative pattern cover sheet.
    Creator: Ridenburgh, William, vendor
  - States--New Jersey: New Jersey (Offsite-box 4, Item 1)
    New Jersey state seal over American flag. Cream envelope with brown ink. Image on left.
  - States--New York: 69th Reg't N.Y.S. Vol. (Offsite-box 4, Item 16)
    American shield with seal of New York's 69th Battalion in center, which is a harp and clover design. Beige envelope with red, blue and green ink. Image on left.
  - States--New York: New York (Offsite-box 4, Item 1)
    Liberty, holding banner bearing title and motto, sits with American shield, eagle, and New York state seal. White envelope with orange ink. Image on left with banner across top and shield in top-right corner.
    Creator: Young, Lockwood & Co.'s Press
  - States--New York: 79th N. Y. Regiment (Offsite-box 4, Item 26)
    Member of the 79th New York Regiment in uniform. Cream envelope with red ink. Image on left.
  - States--New York: Ever ready (Offsite-box 4, Item 24)
    A buffalo. Yellow envelope with brown ink. Image on top-left.
  - States--New York: [Union soldiers from various regiments.] (Offsite-box 4, Item 25)
    Examples of soldiers in uniform from ten regiments with identification key. Cream envelope with red, blue and yellow ink. Image on left.
    Creator: Young, Lockwood & Co.
  - States--New York: The gallant 69th of New-York (Offsite-box 4, Item 11)
    Soldiers at fortification flying American flag and flag of the New York 69th Battalion. Beige envelope with colored ink. Image on left.
  - States--Ohio: Ohio true to the Union (Offsite-box 4, Item 3)
    Ohio state seal. Cream envelope with black ink. Image on left.
  - States--Ohio: Camp Dennison, near Cincinnati, O. (Offsite-box 4, Item 12)
    View of Union army camp. Cream envelope with red ink. Image covers sheet.
  - States--Oregon: Oregon (Offsite-box 4, Item 3)
    Oregon state seal. White envelope with blue ink. Image on left.
  - States--Pennsylvania: Independence Hall (Offsite-box 4, Item 7)
    View of Independence Hall (Philadelphia, PA,) inset over view of tools and provisions. White envelope with brown ink. Image on top.
  - States--Pennsylvania: Pennsylvania (Offsite-box 4, Item 1)
    Pennsylvania state seal over American flag. White envelope with brown ink. Image on left.
  - States--Rhode Island: Dedicated to the 71st Regiment and the Rhode Island boys. (Offsite-box 4, Item 6)
    Troops marching along railroad track. White envelope with blue ink. Image on top-left.
  - States--Rhode Island: State of Rhode Island (Offsite-box 4, Item 1)
    Liberty in clouds, holding American flag and Rhode Island state seal. White envelope with colored ink. Image on left with "union" on top-right in stars and stripes.
    Creator: Tingley, John H.
  - States--Utah: Utah (Offsite-box 4, Item 1)
    Utah state seal. White envelope with blue ink. Image on left.
  - States--Vermont: Vermont (Offsite-box 4, Item 3)
    Vermont state seal over American flag. White envelope with brown ink. Image on left.
  - States--Washington, D.C.: The Capitol at Washington. (Offsite-box 4, Item 1)
    View of the Capitol building in Washington, D. C. White envelope with brown ink.
  - States--Wisconsin: State of Wisconsin (Offsite-box 4, Item 2)
    Liberty, wrapped in American flag, holds Wisconsin state seal. White envelope with colored ink. Image on left. Border and decorative pattern cover sheet.
  - Uncle Sam: Uncle Sam's infallible remedy for all rebel-ious complaints. (Offsite-box 7, Item 25)
    Uncle Sam hold a rebel by the throat and kicks him into the air. White envelope with black ink. Image on left.
  - Uncle Sam: [Uncle Sam fishing] (Offsite-box 7, Item 3)
    Uncle Sam fishing in a pond labeled "secession" for fish labeled with the names of the Confederate states. He has a cannon at the end of his line for bait. White envelope with black ink and applied color. Image on left.
  - Uncle Sam: Agriculture, manufactures, fine arts. (Offsite-box 7, Item 9)
    Uncle Sam turns a reel labeled "Hemp for the traitors, North or South," with rope coming from hemp behind him labeled "agriculture," and going to a gallows in front of him, labeled "fine arts." White envelope with black ink. Image on left. Enclosure.
  - Uncle Sam: Or you are lost (Offsite-box 7, Item 13)
    Uncle Sam holding a flag out to a man who has fallen off a dock loaded with provisions. The drowning man's hat is labeled "south." An alligator labeled "secession" looks on. White envelope with black ink and applied color. Image on left.
  - Uncle Sam: 5 to one ha. (Offsite-box 7, Item 27)
    Uncle Sam as a soldier stands with a rooster and an American flag as Confederate soldiers flee. White envelope with brown ink. Image on top-left.
  - Women: Off for the war. (Offsite-box 7, Item 15)
    Woman, boy, and dog bidding goodbye to a Zouave soldier holding the American flag. White envelope with black ink and applied color. Image on top-left.
    Creator: Wiswell, copyright holder
  - Women: I have no one to send. (Offsite-box 7, Item 4)
    A woman pulling clothes from a bureau. Cream envelope with red ink. Image on left.
  - Women: Change, arms! (Offsite-box 7, Item 19)
    Soldier bidding goodbye to woman and child. White envelope with black ink. Image on left.
  - Women: Home guard. (Offsite-box 7, Item 1)
    Woman dressed in stars and stripes with rifle, backpack and military hat. White envelope with colored ink. Image on left.
  - Women: [A soldier's farewell.] (Offsite-box 7, Item 20)
    Soldier bidding goodbye to woman dressed in stars and stripes. In background, woman and children waving to leaving soldiers. White envelope with colored ink. Image on left.
    Creator: Hawley, Joseph R. (Joseph Roswell), 1826-1905
  - Women: Our hearts are with them. (Offsite-box 7, Item 9)
    Woman sewing. White envelope with red ink. Image on left.
    Creator: Cutter, Tower & Co.
  - Women: My only support. (Offsite-box 7, Item 5)
    Woman washing clothes in a tub. Cream envelope with red ink. Image on left.
  - Women: The girl I left behind me. (Offsite-box 7, Item 18)
    Soldier bidding goodbye to a woman dressed in stars and stripes. White envelope with colored ink. Image on left.
  - Women: [Soldier leaving for war.] (Offsite-box 7, Item 16)
    Woman and children bidding a man in uniform goodbye. White envelope with black ink and applied color. Image on top-left.
  - Women: True to the stars and stripes. (Offsite-box 7, Item 3)
    Woman holding the American flag and waving a handkerchief. White envelope with colored ink. Image on left. Embossed decoration on seal.
  - Women: Let Union be your watchword my brave soldiers. (Offsite-box 7, Item 2)
    Woman pointing to the word "Union," as she looks toward a ship at sea. White envelope with blue ink. Image on left.
  - Women: Officer: front face! (Offsite-box 7, Item 10)
    A line of soldiers look away from their officer towards a young girl. Yellow envelope with black and red ink. Image on left.
  - Women: Our hearts are with our brothers in the field. (Offsite-box 7, Item 7)
    Woman sitting by American flag, sewing. White envelope with colored ink. Image on left. Embossed decoration on seal.
  - Women: The girl I left behind me. (Offsite-box 7, Item 21)
  - Women: If I cannot fight. (Offsite-box 7, Item 6)
    Woman rolling dough. White envelope with red ink. Image on left.
  - Zouaves: The new Zouave drill. (Offsite-box 7, Item 8)
    Five Zouave soldiers forming a gallows from which hangs a confederate soldier. White envelope with black ink. Image on top-left.
  - Zouaves: The latest Zouave drill. (Offsite-box 7, Item 7)
    Confederate soldiers firing a cannon toward Zouave soldiers who jump into the air, legs spread to avoid the cannonball. Cream envelope with red ink. Image on top-left.
  - Zouaves: The Zouave defender (Offsite-box 7, Item 4)
    Zouave soldier in uniform with rifle. White envelope with colored ink. Image on left with indications for name and address on right.
  - Zouaves: The Attack At "Man-asses-gap" Junction. (Offsite-box 7, Item 16)
    Zouave soldier pointing his bayonet at a man with an oversized ass head. Cream envelope with gray ink. Image on left side.
    Creator: Harbach & Bro.
  - Zouaves: The school of the Indiana Zouave. (Offsite-box 7, Item 18)
    Soldier in Zouave uniform cleaning rifle beside slain deer. White envelope with blue ink. Image on left.
    Creator: Kline, A.C.
  - Zouaves: "Forgive me, my friend, ef I seem to be het (Offsite-box 7, Item 15)
    Zouave soldier kneeling with bayonet, in front of clouds. White envelope with red and blue ink. Image on left side.
  - Zouaves: The Soldier's Dream of Home (Offsite-box 7, Item 13)
    A soldier sleeps fitfully on a battlefield with a fire burning behind him as he dreams of home, wife and child. Image covers sheet. White envelope with black and red ink.
  - Zouaves: [Zouave camp] (Offsite-box 7, Item 6)